So now I want to talk about the concept of
logic gates. So what are logic gates? Well,
logic gates are not a real thing. Transistors are
a real thing. A logic gate is an abstraction that
we use as hardware designers to greatly simplify
our lives. This is no different than when I
was teaching you software and I'm like look at
this cool low-level way of doing this that and
the other thing. And you're like oh that's really
pretty complex. And then in the next breath I say,
well, if we extend this object, we get all this
work for free. And now our code goes from 75
lines down to two lines. And that's kind of
how abstractions work. And that's how gates
work. So gates, we don't need to think about
sort of response graphs of input voltages and
output voltages. We don't have to think about
that. That still is a thing. It gates don't
make the whole analog problem go away. They just
make it so we don't think about it anymore. And
that's a problem that the folks who manufacture
these chips have solved in the manufacturing
process. We pretty much say let's make a gate
and then somehow the gates are manufactured
out of analog components. The way we think about
gates is beautiful. We think about zeros and ones
which is very much digital logic and the concept
of digital logic predates computers. Absolutely.
And so we just say oh this this gate this not gate
if presented with an input of zero gives an output
of one and if it's presented with an input of one
it gives an output of zero and that's a notgate
and I like starting with a notgate first it's
the simplest thing we can see how it's built from
transistors but it also is like it's active it's
doing something it's not just copying something so
we'll we'll build much more complex logic circuits
we're going to see much more complex gates But I
can't really run away from history quite yet. Over
time, as manufacturing capabilities changed from
POS to NMOS to CMOS, the way we built a logic gate
underneath the abstraction, all these logic gates
have an input of A and output of out. If you put a
zero at A, you get a one at out. If you could put
a one at A, you get a zero at out. And so there
are uh three symbols like the VDD. There's like
a a 9volt battery that has its positive terminal
at VDD and its negative terminal at the little
ground symbol at the bottom. The other thing we
see is a POS transistor at the top there. It's a
transistor. It's kind of implying that there's a
a switch going on or a valve if you if you want.
The little circle says POS and the lack of little
circle says NMOS. And then the bottom thing is a
resistor. And it's probably easiest to talk about
these in the concept of how they work. So if you
present a zero, let's start with the POS in 1972.
You present a zero at the input, that means that
the POS transistor conducts. And so that means
that the positive voltage is copied to output.
So when you press a zero, it conducts and it goes
to output. The POS transistor is now conducting
both to get the voltage to the output to produce
a one at the output, but also connecting through
the resistor to ground. Now, every time you see
a resistor, it's kind of like a pack. And the
problem is is resistors heat up. But if you didn't
have the resistor there, all the little lines,
the wires, the tiny wires, and perhaps even the
transistor, they would melt. So, the resistors are
there to protect the transistors, okay? and and
protect the wires. Frankly, when NOS is presented
with a zero, that means it's an open circuit. And
so, the nice thing there is when you're presented
with a zero, it just copies through a resistor
the voltage to the output. And the cool thing
there is it's not really sending as much current
to the output because all that output is being
is connected to the input of another transistor
later in the circuit. And so, that doesn't really
heat up so badly. Now if you look at cos what you
have is a a pos transistor at the top and a no MOS
transistor at the bottom and we they they work
in pairs and so in the case of the zero the pos
transistor conducts and the NOS transistor doesn't
conduct and so the there is no resistor and the
voltage is copied to the output. Now let's look
at the case of the one in POS when you present
a one the POS is an open circuit and so that
means that we need the output to be zero which
means we have to connect the ground to the output
that is connected through a resistor but it's low
current because the output is just going to the
input of another transistor. And so if you look
then at the N MOS, we have the opposite problem
when we're presented with a one because the N
MOS then conducts it both conducts the ground to
the output and it conducts the positive to the
ground. But that would be a short circuit unless
we put a resistor there. So there you got a thing
heating up. So the problem is with POS and NMOS
is one of the two states for both of them is going
to be causing heat. is one is causing heat on a
zero, the other's causing heat on a one. But then
we look at the cos. Okay. And what we see when we
present a one and we want an output of zero. Well,
the the NOS transistor at the bottom is conducting
and so ground is connected to the output which is
exactly what we want. And the POS transistor is an
open circuit. So the the voltage VDD is not being
connected and we don't need a resistor. And so
what you see is there are no resistors. And there
is just you have to be able to build at a low
level both POS and NOS transistors in the same
circuit like really tiny. And so what happened was
is NMOS and POS were hot and the the hotter they
were the less dense the chips could be. So once
we went to CMOS and again that was really a qu
not not a question of wanting it. It's a question
of practical manufacturing. Okay. And so at some
point mid 1980s, Intel 486, CMOS became practical.
All of a sudden, you didn't have to have a central
processor the size of a large cabinet. And part of
that large cabinet had to do with how much power
it was taking and how much heat it was generating.
If you put it all together, it would just like
instantly melt. And so you had to kind of take
these transistors and keep them and resistors
in MOS and POS computers and keep them away from
each other because they would overheat because of
the resistors. But the moment that you can take
a the the size of a computer from 10 feet end to
end to one inch end to end, everything got faster.
So and and 1983 is a long time ago. There hasn't
been a major like upheaval in they talk about
like quantum computing and stuff but and that
would be a major upheaval at this level but really
from 1983 to present we just pretty much make CMOS
because once we could manufacture it reliably
we'll do CMOS. Okay. So now what I want to show
you is a tool that that I've built called a CMOS
layout tool. And so this way you can pres connect
them and put them together and simulate circuits.
So let's take a look at this tool. Okay. Across
the top we have a number of things that you can
place in this circuit and then we'll draw wires
in between them. So let's start with a probe.
Here's a probe. And if we connect the probe to the
positive, you see that the probe is reading that
now it's got 5 volts. Now, if we delete that and
we place a probe and connect it to the negative,
it's zero. So, part of what we're going to do in
the not gate is have a switch as input. A switch
is in effect a switch that either goes to uh to
the positive or the ground. And you can imagine
there's a wire running up here and a wire running
down there, but I didn't show that. It's just sort
of like another little it's it's connected either
to the top or the bottom so that we can test our
circuits. So what we're going to do is build a
circuit that can create the logic so that whatever
we have here as input the probe on the left as
input we're going to have output that is the
opposite of that. So these after a while you get
used to these. So let's first put a POS transistor
at the top and then put a NOS transistor below it.
So, we're going to connect the voltage to the the
top connector of the POS transistor. And then we
are going to connect the bottom connection of
the NOS transistor to ground. And then we're
going to take the output of the NOS transistor and
connect it to the POS transistor. Now, I say POS,
the little circle is POS and the lack of the
little circle is NOS. And so the output is
going to be connected. It can be connected either
place but the output is basically connected to the
connection between the two transistors. And then
the last thing last thing we have to do is connect
the switch to the the the grid of each of these
transistors. And now we have it. So you can see
that it's been sort of adapting and changing. And
and the key thing is is that the the POS and NMOS
transistors have kind of opposite logic. So the
POS here is presented with a 5 volts which means
it's an open circuit. And the NOS is presented
with 5 volts which means it's a closed circuit.
And that's what this little green line is saying
that it's a closed circuit. So if I flip this,
it means that the POS transistor conducts and
the NOS transistor no longer conducts. Okay?
And so now the output is 5 volts because the 5
volts is flowing through the POS transistor to
the output. If I flip it, the POS transistor
opens up and the ground flows through the NOS
transistor to the output. And so that's that's it.
That's and you know that's the picture that I've
been showing you that shows the the POS and NMOS.
And there are no resistors in here. So there's no
there's no dangerous heat. So I can flip this as
fast as I like and you can see it flipping back
and forth and it's really activating or causing a
close closed circuit a circuit to close on either
the NMOS or the POS. But we've constructed it in
a way that it's like an if then else for circuit
uh transmission and that's why I kind of call this
notgate you know an electrical if statement. So
basically that was a notgate and we're going to
build much more complex digital gates but then
we're going to build circuits out of those gates.
We're not really going to build very complex
circuits out of transistors, although ultimately
they're manufactured as transistors. And so there
is mathematical logic that predates computers for
like and and or exclusive or and not. And then
there's a there's some there's other logic that we
kind of learn to use because we could build them
with fewer transistors. NAND and NOR. And NAND is
not and and NOR is NOR. So our classic logic gates
come from digital logic uh uh something that was
a theoretical thing that that was a pen and paper
uh well before computers came on the scene.
So the first the first digital logic gate is
a knockgate that simply inverts its input.
Zero becomes one one becomes zero. An gate
is simple we if both of its inputs are one then
the output is one otherwise the output is zero.
Uh the orgate is if either of its inputs is one,
the output is one. And if both inputs are zero,
the output is zero. And then there's the exclusive
orgate, which we're going to find really useful.
It's kind of a it almost like counts its
inputs. Um it's not a counter in any way,
but it counts its inputs. If one of the inputs
is one, its output is one. If both the inputs are
zero or both the inputs are one, the output of an
exclusive or gate is zero. Now, it turns out that
we tended to use we we tended to use those and
or and not in classic digital logic math. But it
turns out that it's easier to build NAND and NOR,
which is really an inversion of the and inversion
of the NOR. Now you could throw a notgate on the
end of these things to make them be ands and ors.
But it turned out that early times we just could
build NANDs and NORs with a lot fewer transistors.
And so the NAND gate is the opposite of and which
means that if any of the inputs of a NAND is zero,
the output is a one. And if both the inputs of a
NAND are one, the output is a zero. And similarly
for the OR, if both the inputs are zero, the
outputs a one. And if any of the inputs are of
the of the nor are one, the output is a zero. It
is literally not and and not or and can be turned
into and and or with one more notgate, which
means that you would put two more transistors
at the end of each of these things. I want to show
you how we can lay out a norate. And and and the
basic idea of these things is that it's kind of
like a notgate. And that's what's cool about it,
except there are two POS transistors at the
top and two NOS transistors at the bottom.
The the bottom set of transistors decide when it's
connected to ground and the top set of transistors
decide when it's connected to to 5 volts. And
there they work in kind of parallel and opposite
to make sure that there's a never a connection
from the voltage to the ground. It's either the
ground to the output or the voltage to the output.
So let's do a real quick walk through of a norate.
So not or. So right now we have inputs of one. Now
we've made the input zero. And so when it's zero,
both are zeros, then the output is a one. And
if any is of them one, either of them are one,
then the output becomes zero. And so it's
not that tricky. it it sort of looks like
an extended notgate in that basically we've got
two POS transistors at the top and if either if
either of them are one that blocks the flow of
electricity from the 5 volts to the output and
the same is true we have in parallel NMOS gates
where if either of them is on that connects ground
to the output. So you can see that when when I
have them both with with both of them on both A
and B on you see that both of the NMOS transistors
are conducting and so ground comes up the but like
if I just change one of them you see that the the
5 volts is flowing through the top POS but it's
being stopped by the second POS and so that means
that the plus five does not flow to the output.
And looking at the NMOS transistors, you see that
the this one is not conducting, but the other one
the the B input is conducting. And so there's
at least one path from the output to ground.
If I flip these, you'll see that now that A is
one and B is zero, you see that it the the plus
five is blocked by the non-conducting first POS
transistor. And the ground passes through the
conducting NOS transistor, the first NOS, the A
NOS transistor. And so it just kind of look at
it. You see that what it is is really just kind of
more knot gates that has the it's either going to
conduct eventually from the top or the bottom. And
now we can have all the combinations of the inputs
that work and by creating this structure. And so
you could create a threeinput norate, a fourinput
norate etc etc etc. So this is just a look at an
upcoming lecture and an upcoming tool that you're
going to use. Now once we have the abstraction
of digital logic, we can start designing circuits
using digital logic design. And all of a sudden it
just is a lot simpler and a lot less cluttered. So
here is a NAND gate designed at the level of a
gate with inputs and outputs. And you're going
to like it. We we're not going to build complex
circuits using transistors. All we're trying to do
right now is give you the mapping from transistors
to gates so that later when we use gates,
you just assume that it's okay that there are
transistors underneath. [Music] [Applause] [Music]